<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>System on SL Notebook</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/</link><description>Recent content in System on SL Notebook</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 11:41:41 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>System Startup</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/system-startup/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 22:46:37 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/system-startup/</guid><description>The boot process In linux, the boot process occurs when initiating the system. It goes from the moment the computer is powered on until the UI is fully operational and ready.
This is a sequential Process
1. BIOS Basic Input Output System Initializes the hardware (including monitor and keyboard) Tests the main memory Normally installed in a ROM in the motherboard 2. Boot Loader &amp;amp; Kernel First Stage: Master Boot Record (MBR) examines the partition table and finds a bootable partition.</description></item><item><title>Filesystems</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/filesystems/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 11:41:41 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/filesystems/</guid><description>What is it? A file system in Linux is the way in which files are stored, organized, and managed on a Linux operating system. It is responsible for managing the data on a storage device, such as a hard disk or solid-state drive, by dividing it into multiple sections or partitions. The file system determines the structure and organization of the files, as well as the methods used to access and modify them.</description></item><item><title>Filesystem Architecture</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/filesystem-architecture/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 11:37:25 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/filesystem-architecture/</guid><description>The Linux file system structure is organized into a tree-like hierarchy, starting from the root directory /. The root directory contains several standard subdirectories, each serving a specific purpose.
Good to know Similar information can be found using man hier
Here is a list of the standard folders in the Linux filesystem hierarchy:
/bin - Binary executables for system &amp;amp; users. This directory contains essential command line utilities, such as ls, cat, and cp, that are required for basic system operation and are accessible by both the system and users.</description></item></channel></rss>