<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Networking on SL Notebook</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/</link><description>Recent content in Networking on SL Notebook</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 14:48:59 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Troubleshooting</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/troubleshooting/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 14:48:59 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/troubleshooting/</guid><description>When network issues arise, having a set of reliable tools to diagnose and understand the problem is essential. Linux offers a variety of commands to help inspect connectivity, routing, and traffic flow.
Common Troubleshooting Commands ping Sends ICMP echo request packets to a target host to check if it is reachable Measures round-trip time. It is sometimes blocked in certain networks to avoid network scanning and hacking attacks ping -c 4 example.</description></item><item><title>Interfaces</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/interfaces/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 14:42:43 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/interfaces/</guid><description>In the world of networking, a network interface is a crucial concept. It represents the physical or virtual point of connection between a device (like a computer, server, or router) and a network. Think of it as a doorway through which data enters and leaves the device.
A network interface can be:
A physical interface, such as an Ethernet port or a Wi-Fi adapter. A virtual interface, created by software, like loopback interfaces (lo) or virtual network devices used in virtualization or containerization.</description></item><item><title>Routing</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/routing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 14:35:36 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/routing/</guid><description>Routing moves packets between networks. A router connects two or more networks and has IP addresses on each.
Routing Table A routing table is a set of rules stored in a device (like a computer or router) that tells the system where to send network packets based on their destination IP addresses. Each entry in the routing table specifies:
A destination network or host IP range The next hop (the next device to send the packet to) The network interface to use Additional metadata such as metrics or priority This table allows devices to forward packets not just within their own local network but also across interconnected networks.</description></item><item><title>IP Addressing</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/ip_addressing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 13:53:39 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/ip_addressing/</guid><description>An IP address uniquely identifies a device on a network.
IPv4 IPv4 addresses are 32-bit numbers written as four octets (e.g. 192.168.1.1).
IPv4 Classes (Legacy) Class A: First octet = network ID Class B: First two octets = network ID Class C: First three octets = network ID Class D: Multicast Class E: Experimental NAT Network Address Translation allows multiple devices on a private network to share a single public IP address.</description></item><item><title>DNS</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/dns/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 13:43:33 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/system/networking/dns/</guid><description>DNS stands for Domain name resolutions and is a system that enables the use of domains (names) to refer to nodes in a network instead of using IP addresses.
It works by establishing a record list, which maps names (domains) to IPs
In Linux, systems normally have several &amp;ldquo;levels&amp;rdquo; of DNS resolution:
DNS Configuration Local Resolution /etc/hosts In all linux systems, the file /etc/hosts is consulted for local IP -&amp;gt; Name mapping.</description></item></channel></rss>