<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Using a Linux System on SL Notebook</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/using-a-linux-system/</link><description>Recent content in Using a Linux System on SL Notebook</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 21:57:06 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/using-a-linux-system/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Installing Software</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/using-a-linux-system/installing-software/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 11:02:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/using-a-linux-system/installing-software/</guid><description>Packages A package in the linux distributions is a compressed archive that contains all necessary files for a software to run in the system.
This includes among others:
Binaries Configuration files Metadata Dependencies The compressed package does not include other software that it needs to run. This &amp;ldquo;dependencies&amp;rdquo; are the main reason package managers exist
Package managers Package managers help with the following when dealing with packages:
Installation (Decompression, copying files) Upgrading Configuration Removal Integrity checks (comes from a trusted source, checksum check, etc.</description></item><item><title>Shell</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/using-a-linux-system/shell/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 21:57:06 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/using-a-linux-system/shell/</guid><description>The shell in linux is a program that allows the user to interact with the underlying OS by sending text commands.
Popular shells include:
Bourne Again Shell (bash) zsh sh Current shell can be determined reading the environment variable $SHELL. Furthermore, using
chshAllows one to change the shell for the user
Assumed shell In these docs, it is assumed the shell is bash
Command types Command come in two types. The command type can be used with a command as argument to verify which type a certain command is</description></item><item><title>Checking the System</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/using-a-linux-system/checking-the-system/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 18:45:27 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/using-a-linux-system/checking-the-system/</guid><description>Below is a list of common operations to check the current status of a linux system
Hardware Some general information about the machine can be obtained by using the uname command. With the -a flag it will print:
Kernel Name Node hostname Kernel release and version Processor type Operating system uname -aChecking uptime The uptime command can be used to determine how long has the server been &amp;ldquo;up&amp;rdquo;
uptime --prettyMemory To check the physical available memory use:</description></item><item><title>File Manipulation</title><link>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/using-a-linux-system/file-manipulation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slnotes.blog.castrillon.ch/linux/using-a-linux-system/file-manipulation/</guid><description>As &amp;ldquo;everything in linux is a file&amp;rdquo;, operations on files are critical to using a system:
Seeing the content of files Several tools exist to see the content of a file:
wc is a utility that allows counting certain characters in a file wc file1 # Print newline, word, and byte counts wc -l file1 # Print number of lines cat is a multiuse utility that can be used to print the content of a file to stdout cat file1 # Dump content into terminal cat -n file1 # Dump content and add line numbers tac file1 # Print content backwards (last line printed first) head and tail can be used to access only the beginning (or end) of a file.</description></item></channel></rss>